<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<preface id="preface.startup">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <para>
  This manual will see you through your initial contact with
  &productnamereg;. Check out the various parts of this manual to learn how
  to install, use and enjoy your system.
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Installation and Setup</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Guides you through the installation process and the basic configuration
     of your system. Introduces &yast;, the central tool for installation
     and configuration of your system. Learn how to set up or modify key
     components of your system and how to connect to the internet.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Basics</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     This part mainly addresses to users changing to Linux from other
     operating systems. It introduces basic Linux concepts such as the user
     concept, the structure of the file system and access permissions for
     files and directories. An introduction to the shell is also provided,
     although you hardly ever need the command line to interact with your
     system nowadays.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Help and Troubleshooting</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Provides an overview of where to find help and additional documentation
     in case you need more information or want to perform specific tasks
     with your system. Also find a compilation of the most frequent problems
     and annoyances and learn how to solve these problems on your own.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <para>
  This manual documents milestone 7 of &productname; &productnumber;.
 </para>
 <para>
  Many chapters in this manual contain links to additional documentation
  resources. This includes documentation that is available on the system as
  well as documentation available on the Internet.
 </para>
 <para>
  For an overview of the documentation available for your product and the
  latest documentation updates, refer to
  <ulink url="http://www.novell.com/documentation/opensuse114"/> or to the
  following section.
 </para>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
   href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" os="osuse"
  href="common_intro_making_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" os="osuse"
  href="common_intro_source_code_i.xml" />
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" os="osuse"
   href="common_intro_acknowl_i.xml" />
</preface>
