<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<sect2 id="sec.support">
 <title>Support for &productname;</title>
 <para>
  Useful support information for &productname; is available in a number of
  sources:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Free installation support for retail box customer.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Free community support
    <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/Communicate"/>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  If you encounter problems with the installation or use of &productname;
  that you are unable to solve, our experienced support staff can offer
  practical assistance with the free installation support for registered
  releases. Nearly all common customer problems can be eliminated quickly
  and competently. You can use the extensive support offered through the
  community, as well.
 </para>
 <sect3 id="sec.support.inst">
  <title>Free Installation Support</title>
  <para>
   Our free installation support is provided for a period of 90 days
   following the activation of your registration code
   <ulink url="http://www.open-slx.com/register"/> or following the release
   of the next version. If you cannot find an answer to your question in any
   of the available information sources, we will gladly provide assistance
   for the following issues:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation on a typical home user system or laptop equipped with a
     single processor, at least 512 MB RAM (1024 MB recommended), and 8 GB
     of free hard disk space.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Resizing of one Windows partition that occupies the entire hard disk.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Dual-boot installation with Windows, limited to Linux Support.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation of a local ATAPI CD or DVD drive.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation from a remote CD/DVD drive
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation on the first or second hard disk in an IDE-only system
     (<filename>/dev/sda</filename> or <filename>/dev/sdb</filename>) or
     supported S-ATA system, excluding RAID.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Integration of a standard keyboard and standard mouse.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Configuration of the graphical user interface (without the hardware
     acceleration feature of the graphics card).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation of the boot manager in the MBR of the first hard disk
     without modifying the BIOS mapping.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Setup of Internet access with a supported PCI ISDN card or external
     serial modem (not USB). Conversely, setup of DSL based on PPPoE with a
     supported NIC.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Basic configuration of a supported WLAN adapter.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Basic configuration of an ALSA-supported PCI sound card.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Basic configuration of a locally-attached compatible printer with
     &yast;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Basic configuration of an IDE CD writer for use with k3b (CD burning
     application) without changing the jumper setting.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Configuration of a supported PCI ethernet card for LAN access with
     either DHCP (client) or static IP. This does not include the
     configuration of the LAN or any other computers or network components.
     It also does not cover the configuration of the computer as a router.
     Fault analysis is limited to checking for proper loading of the kernel
     module and the correct local network settings.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Configuration of an e-mail client (Evolution and KMail) for collecting
     mail from a POP3 account. Fault analysis is limited to checking for
     proper settings in the e-mail client.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Support for the package selection KDE Desktop or GNOME Desktop.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Upgrade from the previous version of the product.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Kernel updates (only official Novell update RPMs).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation of bug fixes and security updates from the official update
     server using online update or the manual method.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   For a detailed listing of the subjects covered by the free installation
   support, check <ulink url="http://www.open-slx.com/support"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   In case you are not sure if your support is covered, please do not
   hesitate to give us a call. We are happy to assist.
  </para>
  <sect4 id="sec.support.inst.contact">
   <title>Contact Information for Free Installation Support</title>
   <para>
    Reach our support staff under the following links and phone numbers. Our
    installation support is offered through call back. After your problem
    description our staff either tries to call you back in the next 2 hours
    or arrange a time for a call back. Please register your product at
    <ulink
     url="http://www.open-slx.com/register"/> prior to your
    support request.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://support.open-slx.com/eService"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      United States and Canada: +1-404-5854-269
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Germany, Austria, Switzerland: Phone: +49 (0)911-8946-0303
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      UK: +44-2030-025-943
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      All other countries (English only): please see
      <ulink url="http://www.open-slx.com/support"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    For the most recent contact information, refer to
    <ulink url="http://www.open-slx.com/support"/>.
   </para>
  </sect4>
  <sect4 id="sec.support.inst.note">
   <title>Important Notes</title>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Free installation support is offered to customers with a valid and
      activated registration code. You can activate your registration code
      at <ulink url="http://www.open-slx.com/register/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The registration code is not transferable to another person.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The free support covers the initial installation on one computer.
      Refer to our Web site for further information
      <ulink url="http://www.open-slx.com/support"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </sect4>
  <sect4 id="sec.support.inst.rec">
   <title>Contact Recommendations</title>
   <para>
    We recommend using <ulink url="http://support.open-slx.com/eService"/>
    to open a service request and to provide us with the relevant
    information like problem description and log files. It helps us to avoid
    misspelled commands, links, or directory names, which often cause
    frustrating problems and are particularly common during phone
    conversations. You will receive a reply soon, providing a practical
    solution.
   </para>
  </sect4>
 </sect3>
 <sect3 id="sec.support.request">
  <title>Preparing a Support Request</title>
  <para>
   We endeavor to help you as quickly and precisely as possible. The effort
   and time needed is considerably reduced if the question is formulated
   clearly. Please have answers to the following questions ready before
   contacting us:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Which program and version are you using? During which process does the
     problem occur?
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     What exactly is the problem? Try to describe the error as precisely as
     possible, using phrases with words such as <emphasis>when</emphasis>
     (for example, <quote>When X is pressed, this error appears</quote>).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     What hardware do you use (graphics card, monitor, printer, ISDN card,
     etc.)? You can get this information from the &yast; <emphasis>Hardware
     Information</emphasis> module.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   Detailed documentation can be found in manuals, online help, and the
   Support Database. This comprehensive documentation of &productname; gives
   guidance to solve a variety of problems. The &suse; Help Center on your
   desktop provides additional information about installed packages, the
   vital HOWTOs, and info pages.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can access the latest Support Database articles online at
   <ulink
    url="http://www.open-slx.com/support"/> or access the
   community Support Database at
   <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/Portal:Support_database"/>. The
   Support Database, one of the most frequently used databases in the Linux
   world, offers our customers a wealth of analysis and solution approaches.
   You can retrieve tested solutions using the keyword search, history
   function, or version-dependent search.
  </para>
 </sect3>
</sect2>
