<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<sect1 id="sec.y2.sw.webpin">
 <title>&yast; Package Search</title>

 <para>
  Provided you are connected to the internet, you can also search and
  install packages from almost all known repositories for &productname;
  directly via &yast;'s Package Search. This module is a &yast; frontend for
  the Webpin package search available at
  <ulink
   url="http://packages.opensuse-community.org/"/>. The &yast;
  module is not available by default&mdash;you need to install the package
  <systemitem
   class="resource">yast2-packager-webpin</systemitem> first.
 </para>

 <procedure>
  <title>Installing Packages Using the &yast; Package Search</title>
  <step>
   <para>
    Start the Package Search from the &yast; Control Center via <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Package Search</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Search for a software package by entering it's name into the
    <guimenu>Search Expression</guimenu> field and clicking
    <guimenu>Search</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    The search result is listed on the <guimenu>Found Packages</guimenu>
    tab. Click on a package name to see the repository URL, the package
    version number and the architecture in the <guimenu>Package
    Description</guimenu> pane.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Double Check the Package Information</title>
    <para>
     Make sure to double check whether the software is hosted on a
     repository you trust before you install it. Also check if the
     architecture complies with your system (x86_64 packages can only be
     installed on 64bit systems).
    </para>
   </warning>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Mark a package for installation by activating its checkbox. You can mark
    several packages at once. You can even start a new search for other
    packages without losing your current selection, which is always
    available on the <guimenu>All Selected Packages</guimenu>. Once you have
    finished the package selection, proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Additional Software Repositories</guimenu> dialog shows the
    repositories providing the packages you want to install. They are
    activated per default. To proceed with the installation, keep the
    repository selection. By default, you remain subscribed to these
    repositories after the installation has finished, so you will receive
    updates from them in the future.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    If instead you want to use the new repositories only once, uncheck
    <guimenu>Remain Subscribed to These Repositories after
    Installation</guimenu>. Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Now select the software packages that should be installed. Normally
    there is no need to change the default selection. Click
    <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Proposal</guimenu> screen summarizes the choices you made.
    Click <guimenu>Customize</guimenu> to restart the configuration steps
    from above. Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> to
    proceed with the installation.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Confirm the next dialog. In case a new repository is used, you will also
    need to confirm the import of the repository's GnuPG key. During the
    installation several progress pop-ups appear that do not need any
    interaction. After reading the <quote>Installation was
    successful</quote> message, click <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</sect1>
